Register of the Arnold E. Jenny Papers, 1917-1953
Hoover Institution Archives
Arnold E. Jenny Papers,
1917-1953
73068
Hoover Institution Archives
5 boxes, 3 envelopes (2.3 linear feet)
Correspondence, diary, reports, memoranda, and printed matter, relating to relief work in Siberia during the Russian Revolution, and among displaced persons in Germany at the end of World War II.
Jenny, Arnold E., 1895-1978
Access
Collection open for research.
The Hoover Institution Archives only allows access to copies of audiovisual items. To listen to sound recordings or to view videos or films during your visit, please contact the Archives at least two working days before your arrival. We will then advise you of the accessibility of the material you wish to see or hear. Please note that not all audiovisual material is immediately accessible.
Biographical/Historical Note
Young Men's Christian Association worker in Siberia, 1919-1920, and in Germany, 1945-1946.
Scope and Content of Collection
Correspondence, diary, reports, memoranda, and printed matter, relating to relief work in Siberia during the Russian Revolution, and among displaced persons in Germany at the end of World War II.
Young Men's Christian Associations.; Germany.; International relief.; Refugees.; Russia (Federation); Siberia (Russia)--History--Revolution, 1917-1921.; Soviet Union--History--Revolution, 1917-1921--Civilian relief.; Soviet Union.; World War, 1914-1918.; World War, 1939-1945--Germany.; World War, 1939-1945--Refugees.; World War, 1939-1945.
- Diary of Arnold E. Jenny during his service for the Young Men's Christian Association (Y.M.C.A.) at Camp Wadsworth, South Carolina and Vladivostok, Siberia, 1917-1920. (Box 1)
- Correspondence with William A. Jenny, 1917-1920.
- Correspondence and other documents concerning the activities of the Y.M.C.A. in Siberia, 1919-1920. (Box 2)
  - Outline of travel and work in connection with YMCA service with the A.E.F. Siberia, 1919-20; 6 pages.
  - Formal agreement with International Committee of YMCAs for service in Siberia, a form designed for use during World War I., dated March 15, 1919:
  - Letter from G.S. Phelps, Senior National Secretary for Russia, assigning A.E. Jenny to the Army and Navy Department for service in the A.E.F. Siberia, dated Vladivostok, June 24, 1919.
  - Letter from G.S. Phelps assigning A.E. Jenny to work with the 27th Infantry based at Verkhne-Udinsk, east of Lake Baikal (now called Ulan Ude), comprising a service area from Chita to Irkutsk, dated July 5, 1920.
  - Copy of letter from G.S. Phelps to Colonel Morrow (full name not indicated), introducing A.E. Jenny to him, Commanding Officer of the 27th Infantry, dated July 5, 1920.
  - Clipping of English language page of The Echo, published in Vladivostok, with feature article on "The Russian Situation - Siberian Army in Grave Peril" (country drifting to disaster), dated July 8, 1919.
  - Another English language page of The Echo with articles on "Denikin's Success" (?), "Far and Near in Siberia", etc., dated July 9, 1919.
  - Penciled notes written by A.C. Krupar, Czech YMCA Secretary, wounded somewhere "up the line" from Vladivostok by Partisan (Bolshevik) guerilla; scribbled because facial wound made speech impossible during visit with him at American Red Cross Hospital, Vladivostok, soon after A.E. Jenny's return from his own adventures in the west. Sharp criticism of Siberia YMCA policy of sending personnel into dangerous Partisan (Bolshevik) areas.
  - Letter from A.W. Smith, Senior Secretary, Army and Navy Department, assigning A.E. Jenny as Senior Secretary of the American Base Hut, Vladivostok (actually covering service to all American Army units "up the line" - all the way to Irkutsk, limit of A.E.F. jurisdiction for guarding the Trans-Siberian Railroad; troops in transit or stationed at the A.E.F. Base and outposts around Vladivostok, dated August 15, 1919.
  - Clippings from The Japan Advertiser of November 26, 1919 published in Tokyo, Japan, headlined: "Vladivostok Station Ran With Blood During Few Hours of Gadia's Futile Revolution" etc.
  - Clippings from The Japan Advertiser of November 27, 1919, "Report Gaida As Still a Prisoner," "Czechs Issue Statement Denouncing Kolchak's Ways."
  - Clipping from New York Times, "Platinum in Russia.", November 30, 1919
  - Letter from Capt. F. Edgerton Guy, Canadian Army, fellow traveler on ill-fated train wrecked at Khandaohedzi, Manchuria, December 19, 1919, July 28, 1919.
  - Clipping from The Japan Advertiser of December 31, 1919, "Christman Day In Cold Siberia," describing YMCA, YWCA, ARC and K of C services to troops.
  - Clipping from The Japan Advertiser of "Semionov Threats Defied By Czechs In Warning Words.", January 7, 1920
  - HQ A.E.F. Siberia Intelligence Section, containing translations of news items in local newspapers and Japanese press on announcement of American withdrawal from Siberia, etc., January 13, 1920
  - HQ A.E.F. Siberia Intelligence Section, Incident near Gen. Romanov's house: Bloody collision between Partisans and Japanese avoided "by an American officer who came to the scene with a section of brave Americans" - quotations from local newspapers, Vladivostok., February 2, 1920:
  - Roster of YMCA Personnel, American YMCA Expedition in Siberia, dated December 20, 1919.
  - Letter from W.A. Smith, Senior Secretary, Army and Navy Department, YMCA, A.E.F. Siberia, releasing A.E. Jenny from service in Siberia, February 3, 1920.
  - Clipping from Buffalo News, reporting talk to the Equality Club of the Buffalo Association of Credit Men, headed "Democratic Is Jap Group Getting Hold.", March 30, 1920
  - Clipping from Buffalo News, reporting talk to the Equality Club of the Buffalo YMCA, headed "Russian Peasants Demand Democracy.", March 26, 1920
  - Clipping from Buffalo Commercial, reporting on talk to the Buffalo Association of Credit Men, headed "Democratic Is Jap Group Getting Hold.", March 30, 1920
  - Clipping from Buffalo News, "Puffed Cigarette in Face of Death" (Admiral Kolchak, Irkutsk)., May 27, 1920
  - Clipping from Niagara Falls, New York Gazette, reporting on talk to the Kiwanis Club of Niagara Falls, headed, "The Bolsheviki, Who And What They Are.", November 22, 1920
  - Photograph of Nickolas (Nick) Johnson, ex-Russian soldier and deserter, employed by American Base YMCA, Vladivostok, as truck driver, movie operator, etc., dated December 1, 1920.
  - Letter from Miroslav Marek (names reversed according to American custom), young Czech soldier helped in Vladivostok, dated University of Nebraska August 26, 1921.
  - Clipping from Niagara Falls Gazette, "With the Yanks in Cool Siberia," as reported by A.E. Jenny., 1922
  - Copy of the Siberian Veteran, Vol. 1, No. 2, Armistice Day, containing letter from Ex-Secretary of War, Newton D. Baker., 1922
  - Clipping from unidentified and undated YMCA publication (believed to be from the World's Committee of YMCAs, Geneva, Switzerland) on a conversation of far-reaching importance, between John F. Stevens (U.S.) and Hampei Nagao (Japan) affecting the operation of the Trans-Siberian Railway. Apparently a review of the book, "What Shall I Think of Japan?" by George Gleason.
  - An unidentified and undated clipping, probably from Time magazine, "Cossack Soldieret," review of the book, "Cossack Girl -- Marine Yurlove" (Macauley).
  - Clipping from The Outlook, "Siberia - A First Lesson In International Politics," by Charles Hodges, New York University., 1923
  - Clipping from the Christian Science Monitor, "Bolshevism Is Doomed," by Count Ilya Tolstoy., April 17, 1923
  - Unidentified and undated clipping, "With the Intellectuals in Russia," by J. Rives Childs.
  - Undated review in The New York Times, " The Decision to Intervene," by George F. Kennan; review by Adolf A. Berle, Jr.
  - Clipping from The New York Times, "The Siberian Fiasco," by Clarence A. Manning, reviewed by Harry Schwartz., June 1, 1952
  - Clipping from The New York Times, " Siberia And the Exile System," by George F. Kennan; reviewed by Harrison E. Salisbury.
  - Exchange of correspondence between A.E. Jenny and Arthur A. Kempa relating to experience shared as YMCA Secretaries in Siberia, with addenda of letters from Henry C. Fry, Commander, Veterans of the American Expeditionary Forces, Siberia, also a statement about "A Boy's World In Two Centuries," an autobiography by Arthur Adolphus Kempa. Also additional exchanges between Jenny and Kempa, March 4, 1969, May 15, 1969, December 12, 1969, September 3, 1968 and November 5, 1969; December 16, 1969, January 7, 1972, and January 15, 1972.
- Correspondence and other documents concerning A.E. Jenny's service as Director of the U.S.O. Club, Oswego, New York, 1942-1945.
  - Letter of addressed to "Dear Family" recounts many significant developments in the program of service to the troops at Fort Ontario. Unfortunately, this is the only letter of that period still extant., April 19, 1942
  - Copy of a North American Newspaper Alliance article by correspondent Kathryn Wood, "Pre-Basic Training, Including Three Rs, Taught at Fort Ontario," contains commentary on service rendered by the U.S.O. Club under direction of A.E. Jenny., dated October 29, 1943
  - Certificate issued to A.E. Jenny by the Army and Navy Department of the National Board of the Young Men's Christian Associations of the United States of America, covering service as U.S.O. Club Director and Director of History Project (at National Headquarters, YMCA, New York), March 24, 1942 - September 30, 1945.
- Correspondence and other documents concerning Y.M.C.A. service to displaced persons in Germany, 1945-1953.
  - Memorandum from Dr. Tracy Strong, General Secretary, World's Alliance of Young Men's Christian Associations, Geneva, Switzerland, to A.E. Jenny, regarding possible contacts with the German YMCA Movement while engaged in service to Displaced Persons. Attached, letter from Church and YMCA leaders of Frankfurt A.M.- Hoechst, Germany, addressed to the Committee of the World Federation of the Young Men's Christian Association, New York, U.S.A. and also a copy of a letter from Tracy Strong to Dr. Roswell Barns, Federal Council of Churches, New York, New York, dated September 25, 1945, (undated); dated August 30, 1945.
  - Letter of A.E. Jenny to Dr. John R. Mott, with attachment of translation of a letter to A.E. Jenny from Hans Mueller, Litomerici, CSR, dated September 22, 1945, dated June 17, 1945.
  - Letter from Dr. John R. Mott to A.E. Jenny, dated October 9, 1945.
  - Letter from A.E. Jenny to Dr. John R. Mott, with reference to A.E. Jenny's communication with Dr. Thomas Mann regarding Hans Mueller's letter (Originals of these exchanges now in the Library of Southern Oregon College, Ashland, Oregon)., dated October 9, 1945
  - Letter from Eugene E. Barnett, General Secretary, International Committee of Young Men's Christian Associations, New York, New York, dated September 28, 1945.
  - Letter from Dr. John R. Mott, addressed To Whom It May Concern, certifying appointment of A.E. Jenny by the World's Alliance of YMCAs "to work in Germany among ex-prisoners of war and displaced persons.", dated October 12, 1945
  - Copy of formal charge to the ten men selected to work in Germany, addressed to them by Eugene E. Barnett, October 23, 1945.
  - Letter from A.E. Jenny addressed to Family, New York, August 11, 1945
  - The same, New York, October 25, 1945.
  - The same, Matawaska (U.S. Transport), English Channel continued from Paris, November 3, 1945; November 7, 1945.
  - The same, Ettlingen, Germany, November 25, 1945.
  - The same, Ettlingen, December 9, 1945.
  - The same, Ettlingen, December 30, 1945.
  - The same, Ettlingen, February 5, 1946.
  - CVJM (YMCA) Program for February 1946, Stuttgart, Germany.
  - The same, Program for meeting for address by Dr. John R. Mott, February 8, 1946.
  - Letter from A.E. Jenny to Family, Ettlingen, March 12, 1946.
  - The same, Ettlingen, April 15, 1946.
  - The same, Ettlingen, May 4, 1946.
  - The same, Ettlingen, May 12, 1946.
  - The same, Ettlingen, continued, May 27, 1946; May 28, 1946.
  - The same, Ettlingen, July 1, 1946.
  - The same, Ettlingen, August 7, 1946.
  - The same, Ettlingen, August 8, 1946.
  - The same, Ettlingen, August 25, 1946.
  - Letter from A.E. Jenny to Family, Geneva, Switzerland, September 10, 1946.
  - The same, Lugano, Switzerland, September 22, 1946.
  - The same, Paris, October 5, 1946.
  - World's Committee of YMCA's Identification Card No. 0555 issued to A.E. Jenny.
  - Military Entry Permit No. 48233 issued to A.E. Jenny.
  - USFET Motor Vehicle Registry Operator's License issued to A.E. Jenny.
  - UNRRA Motor Vehicle Operator's Permit No. 84 issued to A.E. Jenny.
  - U.S. Army Projection Operator's Permit No. 75-164 issued to A.E. Jenny.
  - U.S. Army Driver's Trip Ticket No. GE-20607 issued to A.E. Jenny.
  - A similar form with commentary by A.E. Jenny.
  - HQ US Forces European Theater Travel Order November 7, 1945 (Original travel authorization issued to 10 YMCA Secretaries, for travel from Paris to Höchst, Germany, "By Command of General Eisenhower.").
  - Report on St. Nicholas Day observance, DP Camp Ettlingen, December 6, 1945.
  - Faces, " I Still Tremble For Joy" and "Two Days Before Christmas" - three articles written by A.E. Jenny for publicity uses in U.S. in connection with financial campaigns.
  - Program for 28th Anniversary of the Estonian Republic observed at UNRRA Children's Center, Aglasterhausen, Germany, February 24, 1946.
  - Concert Program in honor of A.E. Jenny performed by children at Aglasterhausen, (Instruments previously furnished by YMCA)., February 27, 1946
  - Letter (original) from Adolfs Vitckofs, YMCA layman from Latvia, DP Camp at Mannheim, Germany, addressed to A.E. Jenny, March 7, 1946.
  - A.E. Jenny's letter in response to Mr. Vitckops, February 23, 1946.
  - Letter from William H. Suddoth, Director, UNRRA Student Hostels, Heidelberg, Germany, to A.E. Jenny.
  - Letter from A.E. Jenny to Dr. Marcin Ettinger, Director, UNRRA Team 94, Ettlingen, Sample of type of letter to all UNRRA Team Directors in UNRRA District No. 1 (H.Q. Stuttgart)., August 20, 1946
  - Letter from A.E. Jenny to Miss Gertrude Larson Sperry, Welfare Officer, UNRRA Team No. 507, Aglasterhausen (Similar to others sent out August 20, 1946 to all UNRRA Teams in District No. 1).
  - Letter from Miss Ella Petersen, Secretary to Dr. D.A. Davis, Director, YMCA/YWCA Service to Displaced Persons, Germany, addressed to A. E. Jenny, August 22, 1946.
  - Letter from Ludovic A. Heuvelmans, Director, UNRRA Team 519, Karlsruhe, to A. E. Jenny, August 23, 1946.
  - Letter from A. E. Jenny to Miss Ella Petersen in response to hers, August 26, 1946.
  - Letter from A. T. Berney-Ficklin, District Director, UNRRA District No. 1, H. Q. Stuttgart, to A. E. Jenny, August 26, 1949.
  - Letter from M. E. Vuaflart, Director, UNRRA Team 506, Boeblingen, to A. E. Jenny, August 26, 1946.
  - Letter from Dr. Marcin Ettinger, Director, UNRRA Team 94, Ettlingen (Original and copy, signed by other Team members), to A. E. Jenny, September 2, 1946.
  - Letter from William H. Suddoth, Director, UNRRA Student Hostels, Heidelberg, to A. E. Jenny, September 6, 1946.
  - Letter from Father Wolak Cassien, Welfare Officer, Sanatoriums of Vatican Mission, U.S. Zone, Germany (original and copy), to A. E. Jenny, November 22, 1946.
  - Directory, UNRRA District Office No. 1, Stuttgart, August 1946.
  - Letter from A. E. Jenny to Dr. Eugene E. Barnett, General Secretary, National Council of YMCA's, New York, with Report on Germany and the German YMCA Movement, March 9, 1947.
  - Christmas greeting and letter from Dr. Marcin Ettinger, Victoria, Australia, to A. E. Jenny, (?)., 1953
- List of lectures given by A. E. Jenny.
- Miscellaneous clippings.
- SPEECHES AND WRITINGS, 1945-1946.
  - Diaries, (originals), 1945-1946 (Box 3)
- SUBJECT FILE, 1916-1973.
  - All in A Lifetime, Raymond J. Reitzel, typewritten memoir privately published by the author, 1974. (Box 3)
  - Germany, 1934-1948
  - Hoover Institution, The, 1973
  - Immigration, 1916-1917, 1965.
  - Russia, 1969-1972 (Box 4)
  - Russian Revolution, 1958-1967
  - Siberia, 1971-1973
  - Stange, Erich, 1946-1953
  - Turkey, 1940-1961
  - Young Men's Christian Association
    - Durham, North Carolina, 1924-1931
    - International Committee of, 1947-1971.
    - Istanbul, Turkey, 1940.
    - Journals, 1962-1963
    - Membership, n.d. (Box 5)
    - National Council, 1940, 1971-1973.
    - New Utrecht, 1942.
    - Retirement Fund, 1955-1973.
    - World tours, 1933-1972.
    - Miscellaneous
  - Miscellaneous Clippings
- PHOTOGRAPHS, 1919-1920, 1945-1946 (Envelope A-C)
  Scope and Contents note
  Contains 236 prints, and 41 negatives in 3 envelopes: 85 prints depicting the activities of the Y.M.C.A contingent attached to the American Expeditionary Force in Siberia, 1919-1920; 90 prints depicting the activities of the Y.M.C.A and the U.N.R.R.A for displaced persons in Germany, 1945-1946 and 20 miscellaneous prints.